Jane Harman Papers, 1960-1998 (ongoing) (bulk 1993-1998)
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Jane Harman papers
1960-1998 (ongoing)
1993-1998
Harman, Jane
MS 387
270 boxes (110 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Legislative aide, White House attorney, Lawyer, Legislator. Papers primarily document Harman's first three terms as a U.S. Representative from the 36th district of California. Types of materials include correspondence, reports and research materials, speeches, journal and newspaper articles, press releases, photographs, and video and audio tapes. Major topics include national defense and the military (including women in the armed forces), the environment, space and technology, California-related issues, the Democratic National Party, healthcare, abortion and domestic and international economic concerns. Notable correspondents include: Les Aspin, Samuel Berger, Justice Harry A. Blackmun, Sen. Robert Byrd, President Jimmy Carter, President Bill Clinton, Gloria Feldt and Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Vice President Al Gore, Judith L. Lichtman (Women's Legal Defense Fund), Sen. Howard Metzenbaum, the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League, Rep. Nancy Pelosi, Rep. Lucille Roybal-Allard, Rep. Loretta Sanchez, Ruth J. Simmons (Smith College president, 1995-2001), and Gloria Steinem.
Jane Lakes Harman was born on June 28, 1945 in New York, New York, to Dr. and Mrs. Adolf and Lucille (née Geier) Lakes. Her father, born in Poland, emigrated from Germany to the United States in the 1930s to escape Nazi Germany. Her mother, whose family had emigrated from Russia, was born in the United States and was the first in her family to attend college. The Lakes family moved to Los Angeles in 1949, where Dr. Lakes cultivated a successful medical career. Harman attended public school in Los Angeles and graduated from University High School in 1962.
Fulfilling her mother's dream, Harman attended Smith College, graduating in 1966 with a Bachelor of Arts degree in government with honors. An active resident of Tyler House during all four years at college, Harman was President of the Young Democrats Club during her senior year. After finishing at Smith, Harman went on to attend Harvard University School of Law and graduated in 1969 with her Juris Doctorate (J.D.). Later that year she married her first husband, Richard Frank. They have two children, Brian, born in 1973, and Hilary, born in 1975.
The stimulus for Harman's career in government and politics came in 1960 when she was an usher at the 1960 Democratic Convention, the convention at which John F. Kennedy was nominated as the Democratic candidate for President. Before launching this aspect of her career, she first established herself as a practicing lawyer in 1970 as an Associate at the law firm of Surrey & Morse in Washington, D.C. She left private practice in 1972 to become a Legislative Assistant to Senator John V. Tunney (D - California), assisting in his work on the Senate Public Works Committee. Harman then took on the position of Chief Legislative Assistant and oversaw legal activities on three of the Senator's committees, Commerce, Judiciary and District of Columbia. In 1973 she moved on to become Chief Counsel and Staff Director for the Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Representation of Citizen Interests. She held this position until 1975 when she became the Chief Counsel and Staff Director for the Committee on the Judiciary, Subcommittee on Constitutional Rights.
Leaving the Senate in 1977, she moved over to the White House as the Deputy Secretary to the Cabinet in the Carter administration, assisting Secretary to the Cabinet Jack Watson. The year 1978 brought a much publicized change to Harman's life. She chose to leave her job at the White House and spend more time with her children. The headline in an article from The Atlanta Journal and Constitution (Atlanta, Georgia) on June 25, 1978 declared, "Woman Quitting Carter Inner-Circle To Be With Family." Later that year she and her husband Richard Frank, then Administrator of the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, divorced.
Harman resumed working outside of the home in 1979 by returning to government service as Special Counsel to the Department of Defense. That same year she returned to private practice as a partner in the Washington, D.C. law firm of Manatt, Phelps, Rothenberg & Tunney. The next year in 1980 she married her second husband Sidney Harman, Chairman and CEO of Harman Industries. They had their first child together, Daniel, in 1982, the same year that Harman rejoined the law firm of Surrey & Morse. Their second child, Justine, was born in 1984. In 1986 Surrey & Morse merged with Jones, Day, Reavis & Pogue and Harman continued to work for them until winning her Congressional seat in 1992.
In addition to her professional career, Harman remained actively involved in politics and the Democratic Party throughout the 1980s. In 1984 she served as Counsel for the Democratic Platform Committee. She was Chair of the National Lawyers' Council, the legal arm of the Democratic National Committee, from its inception in 1986 until 1991 when she left to focus on her run for national office. She co-chaired the 1987 Democratic Gala, an event to introduce the Democratic Presidential candidates and begin fundraising for the Presidential and Democratic Party Victory Fund. Harman also participated in public policy activities, serving as Vice-Chair of the Center for National Policy from its reorganization in 1981 to the early 1990s.
Harman ran for California's 36th District Congressional seat in 1992 and won, earning the distinction of being the first Smith College graduate to be elected to Congress. Traditionally the 36th District had been a Republican stronghold. Though Harman is a Democrat, her platform of progressive social policies and fiscal conservatism appealed to a majority of the voters.
In 1994 Harman was up for re-election and narrowly regained her seat. The margin between Harman and her opponent Susan Brooks was 812 votes. Harman was declared the winner and certified as such by the California Secretary of State in December 1994. However, alleging voter fraud, Brooks contested the results in January 1995 to the House Oversight Committee, bypassing the contestation process in California election law. The Committee began an investigation into the allegations and hearings were held in June but any resolution could have taken another year to come about. Brooks thus decided to drop her challenge in July 1995. As required by California code, the Secretary of State continued its investigation into instances of voter fraud well into 1996 but did not return any charges against the Harman campaign. Harman won the next election in 1996, defeating Brooks by over 18,000 votes.
In 1998 Harman decided to forego re-election for her Congressional seat and instead chose to run for Governor of California. Despite valiant efforts and a clean campaign, she lost to Gray Davis in the Democratic Primary. Harman's colleague, Janice Hahn, ran for her old Congressional seat but lost to Republican Steve Kuykendall. During her time away from Congress, Harman taught public policy and international relations classes at the University of California - Los Angeles. She also served on the Boards of Planned Parenthood of Los Angeles and the Venice Family Clinic.
Harman ran for the 36th District Congressional seat again in 2000 and was elected. She was re-elected in 2002 and remained in office until February 2011, when she stepped down to take the position of Director, President and CEO of the Woodrow Wilson International Center for Scholars. Just two months after she took the position, Sidney Harman died after a brief illness.
The Jane Harman Papers consist of 110 linear ft., dating from 1960 to 1998, and are primarily related to her political life and her legislative career. Types of materials include correspondence, reports and research materials, journal and newspaper articles, press releases, photographs, and video- and audiotapes. The papers are arranged in nine series.
This arrangement largely reflects the functions and activities of a Congressional office while incorporating facets of Harman's life before she became a member of Congress. There are very few materials regarding her personal life outside of her professional career.
The bulk of the papers date from 1993 to 1998 and focus on Harman's first three terms as a U.S. Representative from the 36th district of California. Major topics found in her political and legislative papers include national defense and the military (including women in the armed forces), the environment, space and technology, California-related issues, the Democratic National Party, healthcare, abortion, and domestic and international economic concerns. Generally, there are more materials available from later in her political and legislative career than from the earlier years.
Correspondence comprises at least half of the collection. Also well-represented are background and research materials that her staff used in legislative and political matters.
Notable correspondents include: Les Aspin, Samuel Berger, Justice Harry A. Blackmun, Sen. Robert Byrd, President Jimmy Carter, President Bill Clinton, Gloria Feldt and Planned Parenthood Federation of America, Ruth Bader Ginsburg, Vice President Al Gore, Judith L. Lichtman (Women's Legal Defense Fund), Sen. Howard Metzenbaum, the National Abortion and Reproductive Rights Action League, Rep. Nancy Pelosi, Rep. Lucille Roybal-Allard, Rep. Loretta Sanchez, Ruth J. Simmons (Smith College president, 1995-2001), and Gloria Steinem.
This collection is organized into nine series:
SERIES I: BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL
SERIES II: PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES (NON-CONGRESSIONAL)
SERIES III: POLITICAL ACTIVITIES
SERIES IV: LEGISLATIVE FILES
SERIES V: CONSTITUENT SERVICES
SERIES VI: MEDIA ACTIVITIES
SERIES VII: OFFICE ADMINISTRATION
SERIES VIII: PHOTOGRAPHS
SERIES IX: AUDIOVISUAL MATERIAL
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
Except for the following access restrictions, the papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection:
House Committee files and other portions of SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES are closed for 30 years until January 1, 2029.
The collection is stored offsite; researchers must give 48 hours advance notice.
Audiovisual materials may not be used until research copies are made available which may require up to 3 weeks.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Jane Harman Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit Jane Harman: A Woman of Intellegence.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this finding aid.
History of the Collection
Congresswoman Jane Harman donated her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1998. Additional accessions are expected in the future.
Search Terms
Abortion--Law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Aerospace industries--California--History--20th century; Bills, Legislative--United States--History--20th century; California--Politics and government--1951-; Defense industries--California--History--20th century; Del Amo (Calif.)--History--20th century--Source; Democratic National Committee (U.S.)--History--Sources; Democratic Party (Calif.)--History--20th century--Sources; Democratic Party (U.S.)--History--20th century--Sources; Economic conversion--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Education--Law and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Energy policy--United States--Sources; Environmental policy--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Export controls--United States--History--20th century--Sources; House Democratic Steering Committee (U.S.); Housing policy--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Jewish women--United States--Biography--Sources; Labor laws and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Legislators--United States--Biography--Sources; Los Angeles International Airport--History--Sources; Los Angeles Metropolitan Area (Calif.)--History--20th century--Sources; Medical care--Law and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Montrose (Calif.)--History--20th century--Sources; Political campaigns--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Presidents--United States--Staff--History--20th century--Sources; Public welfare--California--History--20th century--Sources; Smith College--Students--History--Sources; Space sciences--United States--History--Sources; Taxation--Law and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Transportation--Law and legislation--United States--History--20th century--Sources; United States--Defenses--History--20th century--Sources; United States--Emigration and immigration--Government policy--History--20th century--Sources; United States--Foreign economic relations--History--20th century--Sources; United States--Foreign relations--1993-2001--Sources; United States--Foreign relations--Israel--History--Sources; United States--Politics and government--1945- --Sources; United States. Congress. House--California delegation--History--Sources; United States. Congress. House. Committee On National Security; United States. Congress. House. Committee on Science; United States. Congress. House. Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence; United States. Dept. of Defense. Appropriations and expenditures; United States. National Aeronautics and Space Administration; United States. Office of Mission to Planet Earth; United States--Armed Forces--Women--History--Sources; Veterans--law and legislation--United States--History--Sources; Women's rights--United States-History--20th century--Sources; Women in politics--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Women lawyers--United States--Biography--Sources; Women legislators--United States--Biography--Sources; Carter, Jimmy, 1924-; Clinton, Bill, 1946-; Gore, Albert, 1948-
APPENDIX: Committee Assignments, 103rd-105th Congresses
103rd CONGRESS:
Armed Services:
Research and Technology Military Forces and Personnel Oversight and Investigations
Science, Space and Technology:
Space Technology, Environment and Aviation
Defense Conversion Committee of the Speaker's Working Group on Policy Development
104th CONGRESS:
National Security:
Military Personnel Military Research and Development
Science:
Space and Aeronautics
105th CONGRESS:
National Security:
Military Personnel Military Research and Development Merchant Marine
Permanent Select Committee on Intelligence
Technical and Tactical Intelligence
Democratic Steering Committee
- SERIES I. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIALS 1960-1998, 1 linear in.
  This series provides a brief overview of Harman's life as a student at Smith College and her non-professional life. It contains mostly correspondence, newspaper clippings, and award certificates. Of special interest is a letter in the Smith College folder that Harman wrote to her parents, describing her daily life and activities at college. "A Day in the Life of Jane Harman" is a whimsical composition of newspaper clippings and captions depicting a fictional day in Harman's Congressional work. The piece was possibly created by some of her staff members.
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1972-92, 4.75 linear ft.
  This series relates to Jane Harman's non-Congressional professional life. It is organized into five subseries: White House, Publications, Correspondence, Organizations and conferences, and Office files. The White House subseries pertains to Harman's time in the Carter administration as Deputy Secretary to the Cabinet. It includes copies of correspondence with Secretary to the Cabinet Jack Watson, President Carter, and various White House officials and staff. Publications contains articles about Harman or articles authored/co-authored by Harman during the 1970s. Some articles of interest about Harman include those that report on her decision to leave the Carter administration to spend more time with her family and her effects on staff/cabinet relations at the White House. Writings authored by Harman during her legislative career can be found throughout SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES and SERIES VI. MEDIA ACTIVITIES.
  Ranging from 1974 to 1992, the Correspondence subseries includes intra-office and outside correspondence from Jones, Day, Reavis and Pogue; papers pertaining to family business and the Harman Family Foundation; and correspondence regarding political contributions and thank yous. The political contributions and thank yous correspondence is to Jane and Sidney Harman or just Jane Harman regarding contributions (monetary and otherwise) to various political campaigns, including letters from Patrick Leahy, Tom Daschle, Harriett Woods, Barbara Boxer, Robert C. Byrd and various other Democratic candidates and organizations.
  The next subseries, Organizations and conferences, contains materials on organizations with which Harman was involved or conferences that she attended. The items from the Women's Legal Defense Fund (WLDF) from 1971 detail her involvement with litigation on behalf of the WLDF including legal documents and related correspondence. Of particular interest is a case in which the WLDF wrote an amicus brief on behalf of a woman who was declared "unfit" in a divorce case because she worked outside the home. Later items mainly concern Harman's monetary contributions to the organization.
  Women and the Constitution was a 1988 seminar held at the Carter Center. Harman chaired a panel on "The Contemporary Supreme Court and Women." The materials consist mainly of correspondence from 1987 to 1988 about the conference, including a letter from Ruth Bader Ginsburg, and conference materials. Conference participants included Rosalynn Carter, Lady Bird Johnson, Bella Abzug, Geraldine Ferraro and Coretta Scott King.
  The National Democratic Institute for International Affairs (NDIIA) is associated with the U.S. Democratic Party. In 1988 the NDIIA assembled a group to consult on the Chilean elections, and this was the nature of Harman's involvement. The contents include 1988 reports, correspondence and other materials concerning the Chilean elections and international election observing.
  The files are arranged chronologically in Harman's original filing order. The Los Angeles folder contains correspondence from Harman's time at the Jones, Day, Reavis and Pogue office in Los Angeles.
  Office files consist of correspondence from Harman's time at Jones, Day, Reavis and Pogue, from 1987 to 1992. These files are closed until January 1, 2013. Some of the correspondence is specific to office activities but much is of a more general professional or political nature and sometimes relates to Harman International/Harman Industries.
- SERIES III. POLITICAL ACTIVITIES 1973-98, 9.5 linear ft.
  This series contains materials on Harman's political activities since the mid-1970s. It is divided into four subseries: General correspondence, Speeches, Democratic National Party, and Campaigns. General correspondence includes incoming and outgoing correspondence arranged chronologically by year (1995-98) and correspondence organized by type and listed in chronological order (1992-98). The correspondence arranged by year is to and from other members of Congress, agency officials, organizations, corporations and local officials and leaders. It covers a range of topics but is often related to political and legislative matters or projects with which Harman was involved or in which the correspondent requested her participation.
  The correspondence organized by type uses the original designations of Harman and her staff and includes thank you letters, correspondence with government agencies, and recommendations for government appointments. The relationship between this correspondence and the chronological correspondence is fluid in terms of subject matter. Additional correspondence may also be found in SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES in various topical files.
  The Speeches subseries dates from 1973 to 1980 and includes addresses given to law-related groups, various Bar associations and private organizations. They are arranged chronologically. Speeches that Harman gave during her political campaigns can be found later in this series according to the particular race, and Congressional speeches and addresses can be found throughout SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES.
  Harman has been involved with various aspects of the Democratic National Party since her college years and the Democratic National Party subseries contains files beginning in 1980. In 1984 Harman served as counsel to the Democratic Platform Committee. The correspondence folders contain lists of contents in the front of the folder and the corresponding numbered tabs remain in the folder.
  The Democratic Policy Committee published the "Weekender" as a newsletter to keep Democratic House members informed of Congressional happenings. The publication was issued irregularly but it is arranged in chronological order.
  The Campaigns subseries contains materials on all of Harman's House campaigns from 1992 to 1996 and her gubernatorial campaign in 1998. The files are arranged according to the particular campaign and are more abundant for her later races. They contain newspaper clippings, publicity materials, briefing books, issue files, and working files. Audiovisual materials relating to Harman's political campaigns, including interviews and campaign ads, can be found in SERIES IX. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS.
  Friends of Jane Harman is Harman's campaign fundraising group. The files for this group are largely correspondence with campaign supporters, political colleagues, and staff of Friends of Jane Harman.
  Harman won the 1994 race for Representative of the 36th District. However, the election results were very close and Harman's opponent Susan Brooks called for an investigation into voter fraud. Investigations of those allegations continued to some extent into 1996, but no charges were found to be of substance. This section contains correspondence, legal documents, press materials and other information from this period.
  There is one folder containing materials on Janice Hahn's 1998 House race for the 36th District.
  The reference materials included in this subseries were used by Harman and her staff and relate to the various aspects of conducting a campaign. They are arranged by author and then chronologically within author.
  The Campaigns subseries is closed until January 1, 2009.
- SERIES IV. LEGISLATIVE FILES 1993-98, 61 linear ft.
  This series is the largest in the collection, representing the files of Harman's office from the 103rd Congress through the 105th Congress (1993-98). It is arranged in 11 subseries: Voting and attendance records, Bills sponsored/cosponsored, Co-signed letters, House National Security Committee, Legislative staff files, Project files, Subject/issue files, Whip schedules and reports, Briefing books, Legislative Weekly Updates, and Research materials.
  The Voting and attendance records subseries contains records of votes and attendance for Jane Harman for the specified term. They are arranged chronologically by session.
  Bills sponsored/cosponsored also provide a record of Harman's legislative activities in addition to her voting and attendance records. These are copies of most of the bills, joint resolutions, concurrent resolutions, and simple resolutions that Harman either sponsored or cosponsored from the 103rd to 105th Congresses (1993-98). They are arranged chronologically by Congress. Legislative profiles from the 104th and 105th Congresses provide an overview of the status of bills Harman sponsored.